Espy, Watt; Papers apap301
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
M. Watt Espy Papers
1730-2008
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap301
88.76 cubic ft.
The M. Watt Espy papers chronicle the extensive research efforts that led to the creation of the Capital Punishment Research Project and the database known as the Espy File. Espy spent three decades gathering and indexing documentation of legal executions in the United States. His papers contain both primary and secondary sources used to catalog thousands of instances of capital punishment in the United States and its territories since the 1600s. The collection includes material from corrections records, newspapers, county histories, legal proceedings, and books. In addition to the records pertaining specifically to the death penalty, there is also a selection of magazines collected by Espy that cover true crime stories as well as life in the American Old West.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Initial items in the M. Watt Espy Papers were donated by Mr. Espy or his nephew Major Allen Espy to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, between 2008 and 2016. Daniel Allen Hearn donated additional items in 2018.
Biographical Sketch
M. Watt Espy, Jr. (1933-2009) was widely recognized as one of the foremost historians of legal executions in the United States. Beginning with his own personal resources, in May 1970, Espy began the first serious quest to chronicle and document more than 15,000 government-sanctioned executions in the United States since 1608—an effort that formally became the Capital Punishment Research Project. His method was to collect information by obtaining state Department of Corrections records, newspapers, published and unpublished county histories, proceedings of state and local courts, magazines, and holdings of historical societies, libraries, museums, and archives.
Initially Espy accumulated and recorded information about executions in the United States from his home in Headland, Alabama as a part-time pursuit while working in sales. Between 1977 and 1985, however, the University of Alabama Law Center in Tuscaloosa hired Espy to continue his work and during this time he published "Capital Punishment and Deterrence: What the Statistics Cannot Show", Crime & Delinquency, (Vol. 26, No. 4, 537-544 (1980). He also wrote numerous opinion editorials and histories of the death penalty for major daily newspapers, including the Los Angeles Times, The Atlanta Constitution, The Virginian-Pilot, The Columbus Dispatch, the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, and The Nashville Tennessean, throughout the 1980s. In 1984, the National Science Foundation awarded a grant to support the preparation of a comprehensive computer database with Espy's exhaustive research as its foundation.
In 1987, that database became a reality when the Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (ICPSR) published a dataset, Executions in the United States, 1608-1987: The Espy File (ICPSR 51). The portable data file furnishes information on executions performed under civil authority in the United States between 1608 and July 6, 1987, and describes each individual executed and the circumstances surrounding the crime for which the person was convicted. Variables include age, race, name, occupation, and sex of the individual; date, jurisdiction, place, and method of execution; and the crime committed. Also recorded is whether the only evidence for the execution was official records indicating that an executioner or slave owner received compensated for an execution. The Espy File was subsequently updated to include executions through 2002.
The Espy File is based on several ledgers that Espy used to confirm an execution. In one ledger, he arranged executions alphabetically by state and then in chronological order. Espy recorded the name, race, age and occupation of the offender, county of conviction, crime, date and method of execution. A second ledger contained the same cases listed chronologically, beginning with 1608. Espy included just the name of the individual, the crime, and date, location, and method of execution. A third, and much smaller ledger, also is arranged by year and contains post-Furman executions beginning in 1986. There is also a page for new confirmations from nineteenth and earlier twentieth century dates.
Espy's work went beyond simply tallying the total number of executions. Instead he passionately researched and gathered all available background information on those executed, writing detailed note cards, narratives, and the ledger entries, which are all included in the collection. He painstakingly sought confirmation that officials carried out even the most obscure death sentences. Espy innovatively utilized antebellum state and county warrant records outlining compensation for executed slaves in his research. He explored the lesser known area of juvenile executions, documenting cases where children and teenagers received death sentences. Espy chronicled gruesome capital punishments for participants in slave rebellions during the colonial period. In addition, he uncovered botched executions where law enforcement hanged or electrocuted the same man more than once to complete the death sentence. As a further indication of his all-consuming interest in researching capital punishment, Espy filled the walls of his home with photographs of individuals executed.
Although he attended the University of Alabama for two years following service in the United States Navy during the Korean War, Espy never received a college degree. However, through his work, he earned the respect and admiration of academics, advocacy groups, and members of the general public. In 1991 the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty honored Espy with a special award at its annual meeting. His professional relationships with noted death penalty abolitionists, sociologists, criminal justice professors, authors, lawyers, members of Congress, and advocacy group executives are detailed in his correspondence. This group includes such notables as former director of the American Civil Liberties Union Capital Punishment Project Henry Scharwzchild and leading experts on capital punishment Dr. Hugo Bedau, and Dr. Michael Radelet, who once commented that "'[Espy] is widely recognized by everyone in the academic world as America's foremost death penalty historian." (Ronald Smothers, "Headland Journal; Historian's Death Penalty Obsession," The New York Times, October 21, 1987.) Letters describe how public defender offices and defense attorneys hired Espy to research past crimes and executions as part of mounting a defense in capital cases. Prisoners exchanged correspondence with him for insights gleaned from his work and moral support. (Series 5: Correspondence).
Following his affiliation with the University of Alabama Law Center, Espy continued to research and document executions, write, consult, and lecture from his home base in Headland until his death in August 2009.
Scope and Contents
The M. Watt Espy Papers document more than three decades of research from the nationally recognized expert on legal executions in the United States. Beginning as a macabre hobby in 1970, M. Watt Espy, Jr. began chronicling tens of thousands of government-sanctioned capital punishment sentences from the colonial period until the present day. His solitary hobby eventually became an all-consuming passion and he embarked upon a full-time career as the commanding force behind the Capital Punishment Research Project.
In 1987, The New York Times profiled Espy, his work and his "death penalty obsession" stating: "By all accounts Watt Espy's collection is as unique as he is eccentric." This statement remains an accurate description of Espy's materials and the death penalty researcher himself. The collection includes Espy's vast documentation of executions in America, including a series of typed index cards listing individuals executed. Espy's method was to collect information by obtaining state Department of Corrections records, newspaper articles, published and unpublished county histories, proceedings of state and local courts, magazines, and holdings of historical societies, libraries, museums, and archives. In addition, there is aggregated research data, administrative files, general subject research and notes, professional correspondence, news articles about or citing Espy, statements to the media, copies of his published and unpublished writings (including numerous opinion editorials), texts of speeches and testimonials before government panels, a personal signed portrait and autograph collection, scholarly works by others writing in the fields of history, crime, capital punishment, and the legal system, materials from advocacy organizations, photographs of individuals executed, and true crime, penitentiary, and general interest publications and books. Although the materials in the collection include eighteenth, nineteenth, and early twentieth century dates of creation, please note many of these items are photocopies of originals.
The collection also documents Espy's research and thought process over the course of more than three decades. Espy's materials illustrate the shift of research methodologies of the 1970s and 1980s through the twenty-first century. While he began by spending countless hours typing up correspondence to libraries, archives and historical societies, and scouring microfilm, the later portions of the collection include e-mail correspondence and news articles culled from the Internet. Of note, Espy rejected his earlier beliefs favoring capital punishment and over time became a critic of executions, arguing they did not deter future criminal acts and objecting to the number of individuals executed who were not guilty.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Card File Index of Executions, Undated
Series 2 - Documentation of Executions, 1730-2008, Undated
Series 3 - Capital Punishment Research Project, 1974-1999, Undated
Series 4 - Subject Files, 1970-2003, Undated
Series 5 - Correspondence, 1962-2007, Undated
Series 6 - Biographical Materials, 1937-2008, Undated
Series 7 - Writings by Others, 1965-2002, Undated
Series 8 - Advocacy, 1977-2007, Undated
Series 9 - Publications, 1929-2001, Undated
Most of the series in the Watt Espy Papers are arranged in alphabetical order, namely the Capital Punishment Research Project, subject files, biographical materials, writings by others, and advocacy. The index card files are arranged alphabetically by state, then alphabetically by person's name within each state. Documentation of executions are arranged in subseries based on Espy's own categorization: the 50 states/District of Columbia/territories, federal, military, Native American tribal, and international. Correspondence is subdivided into regular communication/people of prominence and general communication, then is alphabetical within those two groups. Publications are alphabetical by title, then chronological within each title.
Death Penalty; Death Penalty; Executions--1608-2004; Executions and executioners--Press coverage--United States; Executions and executioners--United States--States; Executions (Law)--United States--Cases; Hanging; Lethal injection (Execution)--United States; Electrocution--United States; Gas chambers--United States--History; Capital Punishment Research Project; Espy File; Slaves--America--History; Abolition movement--United States; Capital punishment--Moral and ethical aspects; Capital punishment--United States; University of Alabama. Criminal Justice Program; Headland (AL); Correspondence; Papers; Books; Ledgers; Magazines--Old West; Magazines--Crime; Photographs; Newsletters; Newspaper clippings; Legal documents; Criminal court records; Bedau, Hugo Adam; Espy, M. Watt, 1933-2009; Ingle, Joseph B. (Joseph Burton), 1946; Prejean, Helen; Radelet, Michael L.; Schwarzchild, Henry; Smykla, John Ortiz; Vandiver, Margaret; Capital Punishment Research Project
- Card File Index of Executions, Undated; 1; 2.8 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by state/territory, then alphabetically by person's name within categories such as "1-2 people executed", "3+ people executed", "Executions-- anonymous", etc.
  Scope and Contents
  Watt Espy kept a series of index cards, grouped mainly by state, that records information about executions on American soil (colonies, states, territories) since the 1600s. Some cards contain lots of information, including name, place of execution, method, and details of the crime. Other cards have very little information aside from the fact that someone was executed. Sometimes there is not even a name—just "two slaves" or "pirate". There are additional categories for federal, military, and indigenous executions. There are two different card sizes; for the 3x5 inch cards, each state, territory, or other main division is identified with a manila tab. Subdivisions are marked with blue, unlined cards and are intended to mirror the arrangement of materials in Series #2 as closely as possible.
  In addition to Espy's numerous 3x5 inch cards, there is also an assortment of 4x6 inch cards used in cases where Espy continued information for prisoners who had lengthy and/or unusual details regarding their crimes and punishments. Nearly every state is featured in this category, as well as Guam, Indian tribal, military, and federal executions. Since Espy did not have surplus information to match every 3x5 card, the 4x6 cards are a much smaller group. Researchers will know when to refer to the larger index cards because Espy noted "see large card" on the 3x5 size where appropriate. The 4x6 cards do not have any subdivisions and are arranged alphabetically by state, then alphabetically by prisoner name within each state.
  Special notes for 3x5 index cards:
  1. Slave states of the South, as well as colonial states of the North, usually have an extra category of cards: compensation paid to owners whose slaves were executed for crimes. Espy was the first researcher to track that information. However, cards showing compensation paid to sheriffs for carrying out executions are not separated into their own group.
  2. Espy marked certain cards "unconfirmed" if he did not have sufficient evidence that an execution was carried out. Other cards indicate that an individual (or individuals) received a death sentence, but there is neither an "unconfirmed" notation nor date of death. Those cards have been categorized by the archivist as additional unconfirmed executions.
  3. Researchers might want to search more than one category within a state, because some executions fit more than one description. Ex. "Female slave" executed 1858 whose owner was paid $400 would fit the categories of anonymous executions and slave owner compensations, but would only be filed in the latter. Ex. #2: "Man and Woman" possibly hanged in Kentucky, 1820s—would be filed in unconfirmed executions, not the anonymous group.
  4. Card files include military executions and lynchings although neither were a main focus of Espy's research.
  5. Cards that name 3 or more individuals executed are in order by whoever's name would properly be first alphabetically, even if Espy did not list that person's name first. Ex: Dennis Igoe, James Johnson, and Joseph Frampton- Frampton is first alphabetically and is filed as such although his name is listed last on Espy's index card.
  6. Many of the 3x5 card subdivisions identified by blue cards are organized alphabetically, but due to time constraints, the slave owner compensation categories are not alphabetized.
  - Index cards, Alabama to Arkansas, Undated (Card-file 1)
  - Index cards, Arkansas to Colorado, Undated (Card-file 2)
  - Index cards, Connecticut to Florida, Undated (Card-file 3)
  - Index cards, Georgia, Undated (Card-file 4)
  - Index cards, Georgia to Kentucky, Undated (Card-file 5)
  - Index cards, Kentucky to Louisiana, Undated (Card-file 6)
  - Index cards, Louisiana to Massachusetts, Undated (Card-file 7)
  - Index cards, Massachusetts to Mississippi, Undated (Card-file 8)
  - Index cards, Mississippi to Nebraska, Undated (Card-file 9)
  - Index cards, Nevada to New York, Undated (Card-file 10)
  - Index cards, New York to North Carolina, Undated (Card-file 11)
  - Index cards, North Carolina to Ohio, Undated (Card-file 12)
  - Index cards, Ohio to Pennsylvania, Undated (Card-file 13)
  - Index cards, Pennsylvania to South Dakota, Undated (Card-file 14)
  - Index cards, Tennessee to Texas, Undated (Card-file 15)
  - Index cards, Texas to Virginia, Undated (Card-file 16)
  - Index cards, Virginia, Undated (Card-file 17)
  - Index cards, Virgina to Wyoming, also "Special" cards, Undated (Card-file 18)
  - Index cards (4x6), Alabama to Iowa, Undated (Card-file 19)
  - Index cards (4x6), Kansas to Ohio, Undated (Card-file 20)
  - Index cards (4x6), Ohio to Wyoming, Undated (Card-file 21)
- Documentation of Executions, 1730-2008; Undated; 2; 44.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically within subseries.
  This series comprises the bulk of Watt Espy's primary and secondary research and is therefore the largest in the collection. Initially, approximately half of these documentation of execution records were arranged in an organized fashion alphabetically by state, or by federal, military, tribal or international categories and then alphabetically by an individual's name. The others were not arranged in any discernable scheme with a significant amount of materials kept as unorganized loose documents in boxes. Espy marked some files as "not written up," but it was ultimately unclear how these differed from other records. After careful review, the archivists decided to combine all of the documentation of executions together, divided the records into five subseries for executions conducted by all 50 states and the District of Columbia, federal executions, military executions, indigenous executions, and international executions, and subsequently arranged and inter-filed all the loose materials.
  This series consists of state Department of Corrections records, newspapers, published and unpublished state and county histories, proceedings of state and local courts, magazines, holdings of historical societies, libraries, museums, and archives, notes taken by Espy or others conducting research, lists of individuals executed by state or county, annotated photocopies of Espy's index card files, and documentation of executions sent via correspondence. The amount of material varies greatly by individual. Individuals are referred to by last name or, in the absence of a surname, by their given name. In general, date ranges for this series are not inclusive. Although the folders include eighteenth, nineteenth, and early twentieth century dates of creation, please note many of these items are photocopies of originals that Espy utilized for his research.
  In addition, Espy frequently grouped together materials for individuals executed for the same crime or executed on the same day for different crimes. Therefore he often had only one set of records for two people executed for the same crime. The archivists filed these records under the name of the individual whose last name or given name was alphabetically first.
  The respective volumes of aggregated material suggest Espy focused heavily on U.S. state and federal executions, and not military, tribal or international ones. The state subseries is the largest of the five and documents executions in the United States by state or in the District of Columbia. It also includes executions in colonies or territories that later became states. The files are arranged alphabetically by state and then alphabetically by the last name of the individual executed when one or two people received the death penalty. Next are files containing references to multiple executions, three or more individuals executed on the same day or for conviction of the same crime; anonymous individuals executed, such as a "slave woman" or "pirate man;" city, county, state, or regional records and histories, and lists of individuals executed; and unconfirmed or possible executions. At the end of this subseries are files with lists or records of individuals executed from multiple states. For instance, a list of juveniles or innocents executed from more than one state or executions from other states listed in Maryland newspapers.
  The federal, military and Native American tribal subseries follow the same arrangement scheme. The files are organized alphabetically by the last name of the individual executed when one or two people received the death penalty. Following are files containing references to multiple executions, lists of individuals executed, and then unconfirmed executions.
  The international subseries is arranged alphabetically by country and then by an individual's last name. There are less than fifteen countries and one U.S. territory mentioned.
  - State, 1730-2008; Undated; 2.1
    - Alabama, A-B, 1835-1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 1)
    - Alabama, B, 1823-1935; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 2)
    - Alabama, B-C, 1843-1995; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 3)
    - Alabama, C-D, 1883-1959; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 4)
    - Alabama, D, 1832-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 5)
    - Alabama, D-E, 1894-1988; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 6)
    - Alabama, F-G, 1833-1952; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 7)
    - Alabama, G-H, 1878-1995; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 8)
    - Alabama, H, 1890-1997; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 9)
    - Alabama, H, 1866-2000; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 10)
    - Alabama, H-J, 1884-1996; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 11)
    - Alabama, J, 1831-1984; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 12)
    - Alabama, J-K, 1904-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 13)
    - Alabama, K-L, 1860-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 14)
    - Alabama, M, 1884-1993; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 15)
    - Alabama, M-P, 1860-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 16)
    - Alabama, P, 1831-1950; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 17)
    - Alabama, R, 1839-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 18)
    - Alabama, R-S, 1887-1992; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 19)
    - Alabama, S-T, 1899-1991; Undated (Box 1 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 20)
    - Alabama, Sent from M. Watt Espy to Daniel Hearn, Undated
    - Alabama, V-W, 1886-1997 (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 1)
    - Alabama, W-Y, 1894-1995; Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 2)
    - Alabama, unidentified and multiple executions, 1835-2005 (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 3)
    - Alabama, executions recorded in county histories, 1941-1984; Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 4)
    - Alabama, executions recorded in county histories, 1935-1989; Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 5)
    - Alabama, executions recorded in statewide records, 1928-1989; Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 6)
    - Alabama, executions in manuscript format, Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 7-13)
    - Alabama, unconfirmed and possible executions, 1827-1997; Undated (Box 2 (2-Documentation of Executions), Folder 14)